דף *Daf* is דף *Daf* מ"ב *Mem Bet*, and we start on
the very top of מ"ב *Mem Bet*, actually the second word למימרא
*Lemaymra*. So the discussion here is that we dealt with a משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* that speaks about putting water, cold water into a hot
pot or kettle that you removed from the fire, that you can
do it if it's a large amount of water, so it'll just
get it warm, but you can't do it if it's a small
amount of water, that'll get it hot and that'll get to the
point of בישול bishul. *Bishul*. That's the focus of the משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* introduces a new concern. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s concern is that why isn't putting a lot of cold
water into an empty hot pot considered מצרף *Metzaref*, which people told
me the term was tempering, basically after you heat up metal then
you put it in cold water that hardens the metal and that's
a problem on שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos*. Biblical or Rabbinic, but it's a
problem on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. It's like making the vessel. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has basically two answers. One answer is that you
know if you don't put in a lot of the cold water
then it you know in order to temper you have to totally
fill it with cold water. So how much water, but the answer
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* is focusing on is whether we're going according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* or רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon?
*Rabbi Shimon*. That according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* who's
דבר שאינו מתכוין *Davar she'eino mitkaven*, you're not intending for that to
happen, it won't necessarily happen, it's not a פסיק רישא psik reisha,
*Psik reisha*, it's okay. So one explanation is this רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon? *Rabbi Shimon*. The other answer is no, even according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*, דבר שאינו מתכוין *Davar she'eino mitkaven* is
a problem even if you're not intending it. Here the case is
not that you emptied this kettle from water and it's empty, no,
you removed the kettle from the fire but the kettle itself has
hot water in it. So therefore even if you put in a
lot of cold water you wouldn't be מצרף *Metzaref* tempering because you're
not immersing a hot thing into cold water. It's a hot kettle
with a lot of hot water already in it and you're just
adding some cold water. So those are the two answers. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to wrap this up turns to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*
because שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* gave the answer that it was רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* and you're not intending it. And now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to understand if שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* really holds
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. This is like one of
the key questions in מסכת שבת Shabbos *Masechet Shabbat*. How do we
rule about דבר שאינו מתכוין *Davar she'eino mitkaven*? How do we rule
about doing an activity that might turn into be a מלאכה melachah
*Melacha* but you are not intending for it to be so? Do
you have to refrain from that activity? If we were to rule
like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, yes, you'd not be able
to do a lot of things on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. So we
rule like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* and that's basically what
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* said. So let's take a look. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this, למימרא *Lemaymra*, top of מ"ב *Mem Bet*
עמוד א' amud alef *Amud Aleph*. למימרא *Lemaymra*, this implies דשמואל כרבי
שמעון סבירא ליה *d'Shmuel k'Rabbi Shimon svira leh*, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* holds
like רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* because he's not concerned that
you will come to do מצרף *Metzaref*, you'll come to temper this
vessel, you're not intending to do it. Okay. והאמר שמואל Shmuel *V'ha
amar Shmuel*, but doesn't שמואל *Shmuel* say מכבין גחלת של מתכת gechelet
shel matechet, ברשות הרבים בשביל שלא יזוקו בה רבים *Mechabin gachelet shel
matechet b'reshut harabbim bishvil shelo yizoku bah rabbim*, but not גחלת של
עץ gechelet shel etz, *gachelet shel etz*. That here is a very
important principle which the בבלי *Bavli* will apply appropriately in a minute
about being able to do certain דרבננ'ס d'rabbanans *Derabbanan*s, transgress דרבננ'ס d'rabbanans
*Derabbanan*s when there are overriding concerns on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. There's a
whole list of different types of concerns you can have on שבת
Shabbos? *Shabbos*. מצטער *Mitzta'er*, somebody's in pain, I mean even before you
get to risk of life, okay? Or there's a concern here about
היזק דרבים *Hezek d'rabbim*, you have something dangerous, it's in a רשות
הרבים reshut harabim *Reshus harabbim*, people can be damaged, no risk of
life. There are you know sometimes there's an issue of צורך מצוה
*Tzorech mitzvah*. And in all these different circumstances there's always a question
and sometimes it's not so clear that there's a rigorous answer to
it about how much do we allow you to violate not a
דאורייתא de'Oraita. *De'oraita*, but under what what is the threshold you need
and when can you violate certain דרבננ'ס *Derabbanan*s on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*.
Another example is a sick person who is חולה כל גופו *Choleh
kol gufo*, the whole body is ill, has to lie down or
whatever, not just a headache, but it's not a סכנה *Sakana*, right?
So can you have a non-Jew do something? Can you do something?
Can you do a דאורייתא de'Oraita. *De'oraita* with a שינוי shinuy *Shinuy*?
All these different degrees of questions about what degree of need and
how much less than a דאורייתא de'Oraita *De'oraita*, but what is the
you know how much are you allowed to do for in terms
of the degree of need. Anyway, so here's one example. The example
is you've got a burning hot coal in רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim,
*Reshus harabbim*. Presumably it's not a risk of life but if somebody's
going to step on it they're going to burn their foot or
whatever, it's going to be very painful. And therefore it's exposed to
the רבים *Rabbim*. You're allowed to do a דרבנן de-rabbanan *Derabbanan* to
get rid of it but not a דאורייתא de'Oraita *De'oraita*. So what
is this distinction that שמואל *Shmuel* makes? He says if it is
of metal, a burning hot piece of metal, then you can then
you can מכבין *Mechabin*, you can extinguish it so that the masses
are not hurt by it. But if it's of wood you cannot.
Why is there a difference between wood and metal? The difference between
wood and metal is the following, is that for כיבוי kibuy *Kibuy*,
extinguishing, for that to be a מלאכה melachah *Melacha*, you might remember
that for it to be a מלאכה melacha, *Melacha* to be considered
constructive, it's not just that you've put out a fire, that's not
constructive, that's just removing something you don't want, that's not actually creating
something positive. So for כיבוי kibuy *Kibuy* to be a biblical מלאכה
melacha, *Melacha*, biblical transgression, you have to actually create something. What do
you create by extinguishing? What you can create is charcoal. That's pretty
much the only thing that you can create. So you don't have
charcoal by. extinguishing
a hot piece of wood, if you've got a
burning charcoal in the piece of wood in the street and you
extinguish it, you've now made charcoal. You've done a מלאכה melacha. דאורייתא.
de'Oraita, That you cannot do even if it's just to protect the
masses from injury because it's not a risk of life, you cannot
do a דאורייתא. de-oraita Okay, maybe you could do it with a
שינוי but you can't do it directly. That would be a דאורייתא.
If it's a burning hot piece of metal you can because then
you're not making charcoal, so therefore, what?
Is it on fire or is it hot?
Either way, doesn't matter, you're not making charcoal and since you're not
making charcoal, it's not a דאורייתא and therefore you're allowed to extinguish
it to protect the masses. That is the distinction that שמואל makes.
So turning off a light on שבת? Shabbos.
So that is a very good point, that electric light, even if
you consider them, right, to be אש, esh, which is the general
assumption, presumably it is not turning them off is not a דאורייתא
of כיבוי because you're not creating. So it doesn't mean you're allowed
to, but it would mean that it would not be a דאורייתא,
and that very might well be the case. Okay, there is some
discussion about exactly that, about if turning off an electric light could
be would be a כיבוי דאורייתא. kibuy de'Oraita. We tend to treat
it as if it is such, but you are correct to point
out that that seems to be a direct translation of שמואל's idea
of גחלת של מתכת, gechelet shel matechet.
correct. But I was thinking is it maybe different because of actual
cases? Because if you have like a burning... you can actually have
a burning piece of wood, I think it's much harder to burn
a piece of metal, it's just
hot because you're just pouring water on it, maybe you're making smoke
or something.
No, that's not the distinction that's
made, because it just describes גחלת של עץ, גחלת של מתכת. Now,
it is an interesting question that you raise, which is what stage
is something actually called fire? Let's say something is very hot but
it doesn't give off light. We assume that in order for it
to be considered אש דאורייתא, esh de'Oraita, it has to not only
generate heat but it also has to generate light, okay, or not
only has to generate light, it also has to generate heat. We
assume that you need both qualities, okay, but that does not seem
to, and that's why we consider our incandescent light to be אש,
esh, because they generate both heat and light and they're burning something,
they actually are
slowly destroying the metal filament. But whether turning them out is כיבוי
seems to be from this that it would not be. So anyway,
that's what שמואל's distinction is. Now, how is this relevant to רבי
שמעון? Rebbi Shimon Yes?
I just thought about
the distinction between a hot piece of metal and a hot coal,
but it doesn't seem like you run across a hot piece of
metal in the רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim. very often, unless it's שבת,
Shabbos where
it would be heating up... well, unless there's non-Jews in the neighborhood
and whatnot, but okay.
But yet, so are they just trying to make an argument here?
Yeah, they might be just describing. It is true that sometimes, if
you're in yeshiva long enough, then you think that the rabbis are
never talking about practical situations, they're always talking about hypothetical. But they
are, most of the time really talking about real scenarios, but there
are times where they will just sort of do things for the
sake of making a point and making a distinction. And you are
right, I do wonder, how often is it that you have a
burning hot piece of metal? Especially taking Michael's point into consideration, if
you assume it's not just very hot but you assume it's glowing.
Now you could, if you're near a blacksmith's shop, right, and they
get the thing really like red hot, it could happen. So one
does not get the sense... sometimes you really get a sense that
the גמרא Gemara is just being hypothetical. Here, you get the sense
that this is describing a possible scenario. Right. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with this. So the גמרא Gemara says the
following: ואי סלקא דעתך סבר לה כרבי שמעון, ve'ei salka da'atach savar
lah keRabbi Shimon, and if we think that שמואל holds like רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon דאינו מתכוין de'eino mitkavein is not a problem, אפילו
של עץ נמי, afilu shel etz nami, you should even be able
to extinguish a piece of wood. Now why should you be able
to extinguish a burning piece of wood? That's not אינו מתכוין, eino
mitkavein, you are specifically attempting to extinguish it. How is this related
at all to רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon So we'll see that from
the answer. Let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: ובדבר שאינו מתכוין סבר לה כרבי שמעון במלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה סבר לה כרבי יהודה. uv'davar she'eino mitkavein savar lah
keRabbi Shimon bimelachah she'einah tzerichah legufah savar lah keRabbi Yehuda. That when
it comes to not intending, he holds like רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon
When he holds to אינה צריכה לגופה, einah tzerichah legufah, he holds
like רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. What does this mean? You might remember
this from before, right, from the משנה Mishna בבמה מדליקין, Bameh Madlikin,
about when can you extinguish
the burning lamp, if you're afraid because of robbers and you're afraid
for various things, you want to protect the wick, you want to
protect the oil. So here the point is like this: there's another
debate. One debate is, can I do something that I'm not intending
will lead to a מלאכה melacha? although it might? That's אינו מתכוין.
eino mitkavein. That's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda
There's another debate which is: I'm intentionally doing something but I'm not
doing it for the official purpose of that act. So what would
be an example? I'm digging a hole because I want the dirt,
not to make a hole. That's מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melachah she'einah
tzerichah legufah. The definition of the מלאכה melacha. is to create a
hole. I am basically not trying to create a hole, I'm trying
to get dirt. The hole
is happening, it's definitely happening, but... It's not my intention. It's not
my definition or purpose of what I am doing. That is called
what?
Elevator button with light turns on?
Elevator button with the light turns on, that'd be good example.
Right. That's subtly yes, yes. Okay, for now we'll say it's a
good example. It's a little different because there, I would call it
more a אינו מתכוין פסיק רישא eino miskaven psik reisha as opposed
to מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina tzricha legufa, but those who
associate make a distinction between those, that's fine. Let's take that as
an example. Anyway, so, but, yes. So that type of a case,
what's the story? So there, רבי Rebbi similarly, you know, it's somewhat
analogous but it's not the same debate, which is what the גמרא
Gemara is saying here. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is again lenient and
רבי שמעון says as long as you are not doing it for
the intention, for the sort of defined purpose of the מלאכה, you
are exempt. It's not permissible, but you are exempt. If you're digging
a hole for dirt, not for the sake of the hole, that's
not a מלאכה, you have not transgressed biblically. And רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says you're חייב chayav once you dug the hole, I don't
care what the purpose was, that's the מלאכה. So the גמרא Gemara
says that's why, the גמרא Gemara thinks that extinguishing the burning hot
wood should actually be okay, or not okay but only rabbinic. Yes,
you're intending to extinguish it, but you're not doing it for the
purpose of making charcoal, you're doing it for the purpose of protecting
people, right? So yes, you are intentionally doing the act, but not
for its stated purpose, not for the purpose of making charcoal, for
the purpose of protecting people. So that רבי שמעון would say that's
only rabbinic and therefore if you're doing it to protect people, you're
okay. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says fine, so שמואל holds like
רבי שמעון by saying if you're not intending, it's okay. אינו מתכוין
eino miskaven is okay, that's the case of putting the hot kettle
into cold water and or putting cold water in the hot kettle
and maybe tempering it. If you're not intending, it's okay. But if
you're intending to do the act, but it's for a different purpose,
then he would rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda, Then he would
say that מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is חייב.
chayav. Okay, and that's why he could say don't put out the
wood, the burning piece of wood. So the גמרא Gemara says and
then it ends this by saying,
אמר רבינא Amar Ravina says רבינא, Ravina, הלכך, hilchach, therefore, now that
we've introduced the principle that you can go against a דרבנן de-rabbanan
that you can violate a דרבנן de-rabbanan for saving the masses from
injury, once you get it to a דרבנן de-rabbanan level, קוץ ברשות
הרבים, kotz bi-reshus ha-rabim, if you have a sharp thorn in רשות
הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, I mean maybe a, right exactly, a better example,
I was exactly going to say that, a better example is you
have broken glass, right, in the middle of רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabim.
So even though nobody's life is in danger, it's obviously serious injury,
so or whatever, injury, מוליכו פחות פחות מארבע אמות, molicho pachos pachos
me-arba amos, so therefore there's not an issue of extinguishing, but there
you want to carry it away. Okay, so therefore how do you
get rid of broken glass? You sweep it away, but it's a
רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, so what do you do? So you carry
it less, you do little multiple carries, each carry less than ארבע
אמות. arba amos. So each thing is not a violation, right, because
it's carrying it less than ארבע אמות, arba amos, although the sum
total you're going to get it out of the רשות הרבים. Okay,
but that's okay, alright, because it's a דרבנן de-rabbanan, and you're allowed
to do that. ובכרמלית U-ve-charmelis and if it's in a כרמלית, charmelis,
not a רשות הרבים, then אפילו טובא afilu tuva you can even
move it a lot at once because then a כרמלית charmelis the
whole thing is דרבנן, de-rabbanan so then there's no problem. So this
lays a very important principle that you can violate דרבנן de-rabbanan to
protect the masses from injury, okay, and that is a very important
principle in all הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos and these are two examples,
one of doing a
extinguishing a metal thing which is not making which is not making
charcoal, or the גמרא Gemara says if you say מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is פטור, patur, even if you were
to extinguish a wood thing since you're not intending to make charcoal,
even though you are intending to do the act, it's not for
the purpose of making charcoal, if you say מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה
melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is exempt, or carrying something but carrying it
only rabbinically, not biblically, all these things can be done to protect
the masses, yes.
What what about snow removal?
What?
Snow removal.
As long as it doesn't mean I understand ice, but let's say
when it starts to snow.
I would think that's an interesting example if you actually had a
case where I don't know if I would say more if it's
like a concern of like patches of ice. I don't know, I
mean is snow removal היזק רבים? hezek rabim? I think it's more
like ice is that way. But yeah, but I think that in
scenarios where there's concerns that there are like patches of ice and
people can slip or whatever, to do דרבנן de-rabbanan, for that would
be would be appropriate for שבת Shabbos, if it was דרבנן, d'rabbanan.
yes, if there's issues about real concern about injury. Okay, so that's
what we have. But again the larger issue is that there are
two debates, רבי שמעון takes the lenient position on both, but the
גמרא Gemara says you're they're not necessarily linked. One debate is you're
not trying to do something, it won't necessarily happen, are you allowed
to do an activity that might lead to a מלאכה? There, even
if you're not intending and it won't necessarily, there רבי שמעון says
yes, אינו מתכוין מותר, eino miskaven mutar, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
no. There's another debate where you are intending to do something, the
act is definitely going to get done, but you're not doing it
for the stated purpose of the מלאכה. מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, Melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa, you're digging a hole for the dirt, you're putting
out a fire. fire for the sake of protecting people, not for
the sake of making charcoal. There again, Rabbi Yehuda says it's a
violation, Rabbi Shimon says it's not, and the גמרא Gemara says those
two positions are not linked. So שמואל can say אינו מתכוין מותר
eino mitkaven mutar and still say מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina
tzricha legupha like Rabbi Yehuda is חייב. chayav. I should mention that
that's also the רמב"ם's Rambam position. The רמב"ם Rambam rules that אינו
מתכוין מותר, eino mitkaven mutar, מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha
legupha is חייב. chayav. Generally in הלכה halacha we assume אינה צריכה
לגופה eina tzricha legupha is exempt like Rabbi Shimon. Every now and
then a פוסק posek will say, ah, but maybe we should be
concerned about the רמב"ם Rambam who says אינה צריכה לגופה eina tzricha
legupha is חייב. chayav. Okay, but basically, but but but he's the
one that splits the vote. We generally rule like Rabbi Shimon across
the board, both in אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven and מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legupha. Okay. So now we continue. Yes.
This would seem to apply to be have a big deal for
what doctors can do in the hospital on שבת. Shabbos.
Yeah, you mean in terms of דרבננס and דאורייתאס? d'oraissas? Yeah, that's
a larger discussion in general, you know, about because doctors tend when
they work in the hospital to like basically just do whatever they
have to do without worrying about דרבננס and דאורייתאס. d'oraissas.
A lot of things they do are דרבנן.
d'rabbanan, Yeah,
right, you know, a lot of signing of documents is not necessarily,
although I wonder now, I would- did- as things are done electronically,
they are done, there's no longer hand-signing of things? Oh, so that
makes things a lot easier. So there's no hand-signing. Aha.
So that's interesting. So you- yes, so then many many most things
are דרבנן, maybe drawing blood would be but that's nurses do. Okay,
so then nurses have to worry about that. What? No drawing of
blood. Nurses, right. No drawing of blood. Who's drawing the- drawing of
blood? Nurses. Nurses,
right. Phlebotomists, yes. Okay,
anyway. All right. We can't figure that all out right now. Let's
go on. אבל נותן הוא. Avel noten hu. So now the- now
we're going to the next line in the משנה. mishna. The משנה
mishna, says that
you can take-
you can- you can take this cold water and you can put
it into- into again this hot kettle that
has- or into a cup in order to make the water warm.
So you can take cold water and put it into hot water
to warm it up, but not to get it hot, not to
get it יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, which would be a
form of cooking. Okay. So the point is that the quantity of
cold water that you put in is so much that it's not
going to get heated- it's not going to get to a point
of being יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, it'll just get to
a point of being warm. So the גמרא Gemara's now figures that
out. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught in
a ברייתא. Beraita. נותן אדם חמין לתוך הצונן, Noten adam chamin letoch
hatzonen, you can put hot water into cold
water. ולא הצונן לתוך החמין. Velo hatzonen letoch hachamin. דברי בית שמאי.
Divrei Beit Shammai. That's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says. ובית הלל
אומרים, Uveit Hillel omrim, ובית הלל Uveit Hillel says, בין חמין לתוך
הצונן בין צונן לתוך החמין, bein chamin letoch hatzonen bein tzonen letoch
hachamin, whether hot into cold or cold into hot. Now, why should
this matter? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot have two different explanations.
רש"י Rashi says
there's a discussion in the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim and elsewhere,
which primarily has an issue for כשרות, kashrut,
which is
whether we say עילאה גבר ila'ah gavar or תתאה גבר. tata'ah gavar.
When you put hot into cold and everything- עילאה גבר, ila'ah gavar,
the top thing wins out, or תתאה גבר, tata'ah gavar, the bottom
thing wins out. When you put hot water into cold or hot
food into cold food or whatever, and we know what happens, right?
What happens is that basically the heat sort of spreads and- and
that the sort of temperatures even out. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara
wants to know which one is winning. So is it that when
you put the cold into hot, the hot water heats up the
cold water, the bottom thing wins and it gets it warm? Or
is it that the- that the cold water is cooling off the
hot water? Okay, we might say both are happening. If anything, we
would probably say, if we had to pick, we would say the
bottom thing is winning out because heat rises, right? So if the
hot is more, you know, sort of going into the cold. Anyway,
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. And רש"י Rashi says that's what- so
I won't sort of worry you about that whole סוגיא, sugya, but
רש"י Rashi says that's what's going on here. The difference is if
you put cold water into hot water, the hot water wins, the
bottom thing wins, and the bottom heats up the cold water and
then it's a problem of בישול. bishul. Okay, but if you reverse
it, you put hot into cold, then the cold water's on the
bottom, it's cooling off the hot, and therefore it's not a problem
of בישול. You see sort of how- how that's working somewhat, yes?
The logic there? Anyway, that's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot says
that's not what's going on here at all. What's going on here
is an assumption that if you're putting A into B, the thing
that you're putting it into, B, is what is the majority. Like
you've got a pot filled with something and you put a little
something else into it. So therefore, the thing at the bottom win-
is more significant not because of a general assumption that the bottom
affects the top but because if there's more of it, it's clearly
going to be the one that's having the greater impact. So if
you put a little bit of cold water into hot water, that's
a problem because basically it's heating up the cold water. There's a
lot of hot water, there's a little bit of cold water, it's
heating up the cold water and it's maybe getting it to the
point where it's considered cooking. But if it's the reverse, you have
a lot of cold water and you put in a little bit
of hot water,
clearly it's- Everything is going to it's going to cool it off.
Okay? So basically the difference is not because it's on the bottom
in principle that that makes it more significant, but because we're assuming
that what's on the bottom what you're putting it into, the majority
of the water is the stuff that's in the ves in the
existing vessel not what's going not what's now being put into the
vessel. Okay? So that's the difference. So let's read that again. נותן
אדם חמין לתוך צונן noten adam chamim letoch tzonen and you can
put hot water into cold, I'll read it תוספות' Tosafos way for
simplicity's sake, so there's a lot of cold water, you can put
a little hot water into it, because then it'll just cool down.
ולא צונן לתוך חמין velo tzonen letoch chamim and you can't put
a little cold water into a lot of hot water, because then
you're going to be heating up the hot water. דברי בית שמאי,
divrei Beit Shammai, that's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says. ובית הלל
אומרים u-Beit Hillel omrim and בית הלל Beit Hillel isn't concerned.
בין חמין לתוך צונן ובין צונן לתוך חמין bein chamim letoch tzonen
uvein tzonen letoch chamim either way. Now why is בית הלל Beit
Hillel not concerned? I mean if you put a little cold water
in a lot of hot water, it's going to heat up the
cold water. So now it's going to say במה
דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim when is that true? בכוס. bekos. If
it's not in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, it's not in a
vessel that's heated on the fire, it's in a cup. Okay, you
took your kettle, you poured your kettle from your kettle into your
teacup, you got scalding water in your teacup, you can let's say
I don't know drop an ice cube in it or put a
little cold water to cool it off. Why is that okay? Isn't
it going to heat up the cold water? Yeah, but it's a
כלי שני, kli sheni, it's a כוס, kos, it's not from something
that was directly on the fire. And therefore as we've already learned,
we're not concerned as a general rule about cooking if something is
not in the כלי ראשון, kli rishon, is not in the vessel
that was on the fire. Okay? So that scenario's clear? You got
boiling hot water in your teacup, בית הלל Beit Hillel says I'll
let you put cold water, a little cold water in. Ah, it'll
get it hot? I don't care, it's only a teacup, it's only
a כוס, kos, it's not the thing that was on the fire.
אבל באמבטי aval be-ambati
but if it's in your bath, remember we spoke about the bath
yesterday, so that maybe is a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, then חמין
לתוך צונן ולא צונן לתוך חמין. chamim letoch tzonen velo tzonen letoch
chamim. Then בית הלל Beit Hillel agrees to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
To put some cold water into your bath, if that's a כלי
ראשון, kli rishon, you can't put cold water in a hot bath,
that'll heat it up, that'll be like cooking. Okay, so that's a
כלי ראשון. kli rishon. That's how רש"י Rashi says the issue is.
תוספות Tosafos says the difference is not that, even if we're talking
about a bath that's a כלי שני, kli sheni, there's a difference.
תוספות Tosafos says which is that the water for your bath you
usually will get significantly hotter than the water you're going to be
drinking. So I don't know if that's true necessarily.
Okay, maybe my cup of tea wasn't a good example, I don't
know. Anyway תוספות Tosafos just says that the issue here is that
the water is so much hotter, so therefore it just doesn't look
as good even if technically it's a כלי שני, kli sheni, but
רש"י Rashi says the reason the אמבטי ambati is worse is that
it's a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. Okay? So that's the first issue.
Then would it be a problem with the tea then based on
what you just said a second ago?
Maybe according to the way תוספות Tosafos reads it. Okay, anyway, so
that's okay. אבל באמבטי חמין לתוך צונן ולא צונן לתוך חמין, aval
be-ambati chamim letoch tzonen velo tzonen letoch chamim, then
in the bath it can only be hot into cold, cold into
hot not, because that is, I'll read it רש"י's Rashi way, a
כלי ראשון, kli rishon, and that would be a problem. ורבי שמעון
בן מנסיא אוסר. v'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya oser. רבי שמעון בן מנסיא
Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya says even even that is forbidden, presumably meaning
that in the bath in the כלי ראשון kli rishon you can't
even put hot into cold, you can't even put hot into cold.
אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא. amar Rav Nachman halacha
k'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya. We rule that way. So in the bath
you can't even do hot into cold. סבר רב יוסף למימר. savar
Rav Yosef l'meimar. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef thought to
say ספל הרי הוא כאמבטי. safal harei hu k'ambati.
A ספל safal which is like a basin, right, a type of
thing you put hot water into to wash your hands and your
face.
Okay, so a basin, is that what it's called, a basin? Okay,
a basin is like a bath. Same הלכה halacha by a basin
about whether you can put hot into cold, cold into hot. So
according to רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, in a
basin you can't put hot into cold or cold into hot. סבר
רב יוסף למימר ספל הרי הוא כאמבטי. savar Rav Yosef l'meimar safal
harei hu k'ambati. He thought to say that it was the same,
it's basically something you bathe in, we'll give it the same הלכה,
halacha, even though technically that's a כלי שני, kli sheni, and the
אמבטי ambati is a bath is a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, but
they're both used for bathing purposes, we'll have the same הלכה. halacha.
Okay, so if that's true, אמר ליה אביי. amar leh Abaye. So
אביי Abaye said תני tani one minute, you can't say that. Because
תני רבי חייא ספל אינו כאמבטי. tani Rabbi Chiyya safal eino k'ambati.
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya has a ברייתא Baraita that says the basin
is not like the bath. Even if you're strict by the bath
because it's a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, you're not going to be
strict by the ספל safal which is a כלי שני. kli sheni.
Fine. So now the גמרא Gemara just sort of doubles back and
says the following: ולמאי דסלקא דעתך u-l'mai d'salka daitach that which we
thought to say מעיקרא me'ikara initially דספל
הרי הוא כאמבטי desafal harei hu k'ambati that a ספל safal is
just like a bath. Number one, and אמר רב נחמן הלכה כרבי
שמעון בן מנסיא ve'amar Rav Nachman halacha k'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya and
number two we rule like רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya who says that in a bath you can't even put hot
water into cold. So now you combine the two. In a bath
you can't put hot water into cold, and a basin is like
a bath. So even in a basin you can't put hot water
into cold. So if that's true,
אלא בשבת ורחיצה בחמין ליכא. ela be-shabbat v'rechitza be-chamim leika. So you'll
never be able to bathe in hot water on שבת Shabbos. even
your hands and face. Because what would you do? How would you
basically sort of, you know, clean yourself? You'd take a basin, you'd
pour in it hot water, presumably that in general would be too
boiling hot, so you'd add some cold water, you'd get it to
a right temperature, and then you'd put it on your hands and
on your face. But if you're saying that a ספל, safal, the
basin, is like a bath, when you would think we rejected it,
but you thought to say a basin was like a bath, and
you say we rule like רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya, that in the bath you can't mix hot and cold or
cold into hot, how are you ever going to be able to
use your to get to bathe yourself, to wash your hands and
feet and face on שבת? Shabbos, Okay, so that was the question.
So the גמרא Gemara says, by the way, it's important to realize
that, you know, warm water is the combination of hot and cold,
I mean I know you know that, but I just say this
because,
you know, on שבת, Shabbos? you know, the, you know, if you
are if you're assuming that, I won't get into the issues right
now, but in an apartment building or in a house or whatever,
in some circumstances whatever, you can't use hot water on שבת. Shabbos,
The consideration of using hot water on שבת Shabbat is that when,
I mentioned this before, that when you run the hot water, what
happens is it draws out the hot water from your hot water
heater, and then one of two things could happen. It could be
that it lowers the temperature of the water in the hot water
heater so that now there's the entire temperature of all of that
falls below a certain threshold and then the fire lights up again
and it causes the fire to turn on, okay? So that's a
problem, but that might be גרמא, grama, indirect, and you're not intending.
The bigger issue is that when you remove hot water from the
hot water heater, right, cold water feeds into the hot water heater
and then gets heated up in the hot water heater. When you
remove water, it's all a closed system, so when you open up
your spigot and the hot water comes out, new cold water comes
in. If the new cold water is coming in and the water
at the bottom where the cold water is coming into is יד
סולדת בו, yad soledes bo, you're bringing cold water into יד סולדת
yad soledes hot water and you're cooking it. And that's the problem
of using your hot water. Now, some people say that in an
apartment building it's not an issue because there are so many people
in the apartment building that are non-observant and using their hot water
on שבת, Shabbat. that you can assume that at least it's possible,
it's at least it's not a פסיק רישא, at least it's, you
know, that there'll be a layer of cold water at the bottom
that won't be יד סולדת בו yad soledes bo and the new
water that comes in will be coming into non-יד סולדת בו yad
soledes bo water. At least that's a reasonable possibility. So anyway, there's
some discussions about whether you can make that assumption or not. In
a house, it's a little bit more complicated because if you're nobody
is using the hot water because the first person to use it
gets the water hot when nobody is using it, then there is
hot water at the bottom and by turning it on you're heating
up you're bringing cold water into hot water and it's cooking and
so on. So anyway, those are some of the issues about hot
water on שבת. Shabbat, So let's assume, without giving you a final
answer, though, let's assume that you're don't want to use hot water
on שבת. Fine. You say, I won't use hot water, I'll just
use warm water. I'll take my faucet, you know, those faucets that,
like, are not the two things but you move the thing. I'll
just move it at the warm angle. So I'll just use warm
water on שבת, so it's not a problem. Of course, the problem
is there's no warm pipe. The warm when you put it on
the warm thing, it comes in mixing the hot water and the
cold water. So if you can't use the hot water, you can't
use the warm water either, okay? You'd be surprised people don't realize
that. Anyway, moving on.
Right. So moving on. So the point here is he says, if
the way we get warm water to use is by taking this
basin and mixing hot and cold water and you're telling me it's
like the bath and it doesn't matter which order you can go,
then how do you ever get the warm water you're going to
use for bathing on שבת?
You can use hot water and just let it
cool off a little bit. All right, you're right, you could. Or
don't heat the water, get the water so hot to begin with.
But presumably that was just not the way they did things and
the גמרא Gemara is like, not like saying it's impossible, but it's
like astounded that you mean to say I can't just normally use
a basin on שבת, I have to do some crazy type of
a thing? So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So let's see what
the answer is.
Okay.
So assuming that we in the when we were thinking we rejected
it, but if we were thinking that a basin was like a
bath and a bath doesn't matter which order, so אלא בשבת ורחיצה
בחמין ליכא, ela b'Shabbos v'rechitza b'chamin leika, how are you ever going
to bathe in, you know, wash yourself in hot water? So the
גמרא Gemara says no. מי סברת רבי שמעון אסיפא קאי? mi savrat
Rabbi Shimon aseifa kai?
What makes you think that when רבי שמעון
says
that, what do you call it, רבי שמעון says it's forbidden, he's
going on the end, which means רבי שמעון בן מנסיא? Rabbi Shimon
ben Menasya? When he says אוסר, oser, that he's going on the
end, which means that he is forbidding hot into cold or cold
into hot in the bath. That's what you're assuming. No, ארישא קאי.
areisha kai.
He's going on the first half of the משנה. mishna, בית הלל
מתירין בין בחמין לתוך צונן ובין צונן לתוך חמין, Beis Hillel matirin
bein b'chamin l'toch tzonen u'vein tzonen l'toch chamin, that בית הלל Beis
Hillel permits whether hot into cold or cold into hot if it's
in a כוס, kos, if it's not in a כלי ראשון, kli
rishon, if it's in a vessel. ורבי שמעון בן מנסיא אוסר צונן
לתוך חמין. v'Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya oser tzonen l'toch chamin. And רבי
שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya says no, even in a
כוס, kos, even in a second vessel, it can only be hot
into cold, cold into hot will not be acceptable. If it's in
a כוס, kos, it's like a cup, it's a second
vessel. So that's exactly what
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says. So גמרא Gemara, says, לימא רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא דאמר כבית שמאי? leima Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya d'amar k'Beis
Shammai? So that's exactly what
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, that even Okay, so basically what do
you have? You basically have the following. In a second vessel, in
a כוס, kos, like you have your boiling hot water for your
tea, you can add cold water, even if it's cold into hot,
even if it gets the cold water into a point of יד
סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, because it's a כלי שני, kli sheni,
and this is a big principle we're going to which we're going
to continue when we get to the next משנה, mishna which we
saw yesterday as a general rule, you're not concerned about a כלי
שני. kli sheni. That's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says, that's the
way we would rule. בית שמאי Beit Shammai wouldn't allow it, he
would be concerned that it looks too much like cooking, but בית
הלל Beit Hillel says it's fine, it's a כלי שני. kli sheni.
The only issue is the bath, and the bath there because it's
a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, there you cannot put the cold water
into the hot because you will be heating up the hot water
and we say that the basin, which is a כלי שני, kli
sheni, is not like the bath. So at the end of the
day, it's very simple. כלי ראשון kli rishon is a problem, כלי
שני kli sheni is not. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei de'Rav
Yehoshua, so Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua said,
חזינא ליה לרבא, chazina lei le'Rava, I saw Rava, דלא קפיד אמנא.
d'lo kapid amana. He was not concerned about the vessel, presumably, some
don't have the word, the word אמנא. amana. He wasn't concerned, meaning
he didn't, he didn't care whether it was, was cold into hot,
hot into cold. Let's take a look at how the גמרא Gemara
proves it. מדתני רבי חייא mi'detani Rabbi Chiyya because Rabbi Chiyya taught,
נותן אדם קיתון של מים לתוך ספל של מים, noten adam kiton
shel mayim l'toch safal shel mayim, you can put a, you can
put a like a flask of water into a ספל, safal, again
this basin of water, בין חמין לתוך צונן בין צונן לתוך חמין,
bein chamin l'toch tzonen bein tzonen l'toch chamin, whether hot into cold
or cold into hot. Now that's really fine because the ספל safal
is a כלי שני. kli sheni. So basically as long as it's
a כלי שני, kli sheni, he didn't care whether it was hot
into cold or cold into hot, sort of just like בית הלל
Beit Hillel saying that a ספל safal is like a כוס, kos,
it's a כלי שני, kli sheni, it's not like the bath, it's
not a problem. So אמר ליה רב הונא לרב אשי, amar lei
Rav Huna l'Rav Ashi, so Rav Huna said to Rav Ashi, דילמא
שאני התם דמיפסק כלי? dilma shani hatam d'mifsek kli? Maybe there he
was willing to do cold into hot because there was, it wasn't
pouring the cold water straight into the hot. You took a flask
of cold water and you submerged it in hot water. The likelihood
there that the hot water will heat up the cold water in
the flask is much less than if the cold water was poured
straight into the hot water, right? So you can't prove anything from
that case. So he said,
אמר ליה מערה איתמר. amar lei me'areh itmar. No, it wasn't said
you can place the flask into the hot water, it says you
could pour the flask into the hot water. מערה אדם קיתון של
מים לתוך ספל של מים, me'areh adam kiton shel mayim l'toch safal
shel mayim, you can pour a flask of water into this basin
of hot water, בין חמין לתוך צונן בין צונן לתוך חמין, bein
chamin l'toch tzonen bein tzonen l'toch chamin, whether hot into cold or
cold into hot. So once again reaffirming that if it is not
in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, whether it's in a cup, whether
it's in a basin, as long as it's not in a כלי
ראשון, kli rishon, even cold water into hot is okay. Although the
cold water gets to be יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, might
get to be, you know, very, very hot, it is not considered
cooking because it is in a כלי שני, kli sheni, in the
second vessel, not in the first vessel. Yes.
Now for, for bath though. Yes. Are they going to rule that
way?
In terms of, of taking a bath on שבת or what do
you mean? Oh no, for a bath, no, if the bath is
a כלי ראשון kli rishon and it was directly heated, then no,
then that's the problem about putting.
But if the bath is, for instance, say portable hot tub that
is a כלי שני. kli sheni.
Well, then the answer would in theory be yes, although תוספות, Tosafot,
as I said before, reads the גמרא Gemara, that even if the
bath is a כלי שני, kli sheni, because the water usually gets
much hotter, maybe we would make a גזירה gezeira and so on,
but in principle the answer is that if it's a כלי שני,
kli sheni, it's not a problem. Okay, what we are now going
to see as this next משנה, mishna this next משנה mishna. combined
with what we learned, you learned like yesterday or two days ago,
is really like the key about defining the parameters of cooking on
שבת. What did we learn the other day? I think it was
two days ago, was three basic principles. Number one was, was
what we've been talking about, כלי ראשון. kli rishon. It's only cooking
if it's in the vessel that was on the fire, not in
a כלי שני. kli sheni. Number two is the issue about יד
סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. I'm sorry, before I get to יד,
yad, number two is the issue that it's only when it's heated
by the sun, not heated by another source like the, I mean,
only by heated by a fire, בישול אור, bishul ur, not בישול
חמה, bishul chama, not heated by the sun or something else like
חמי טבריה. chamei Tverya. And number three is יד סולדת בו. yad
soledet bo. Only if the water gets to the point where it
is like, not scalding, but יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, I
don't know, 110 degrees or something, something that you couldn't keep your
hands in it for a long period of time. Now as I
said at that time, that גמרא Gemara was when is it considered
like a cooked water? It was not the question of when will
the water be able to cook something else? So let's take a
look now at this משנה mishna where we once again look primarily
at those issues, primarily at the issue about כלי ראשון, kli rishon,
כלי שני, kli sheni, but a little bit also at the question
about the heat of the water. So let's take a look at
the משנה. Mishnah, Here's what the משנה Mishnah, says. אלפס וקדירה, Alpas
u'kedeira, an אלפס alpas and a קדירה, kedeira, these are two different
types of pots that would go straight on a fire,
שהעבירן מרותחין. she'he'eviran merotchin. You removed them while they were boiling off
of the flame. So they're now not on the flame, but they're
כלי ראשון Kli Rishon and the water is רותח, rote'ach, boiling. Okay.
לא יתן
לתוכן תבלין. Lo yiten letochan tavlin. So now you've got your nice
chicken soup which you've removed from your pot from your flame, it's
in the pot, okay, it's boiling, don't start now adding some spices,
some salt, some pepper, some onions, don't add spices to it at
this stage. Why? Because you'll be cooking those spices. Okay, you've got
a כלי ראשון, Kli Rishon, you've got boiling hot liquid, if you
put spices in it you will be cooking it. אבל Aval says
the משנה, Mishnah נותן הוא לתוך הקערה או לתוך התמחוי. noten hu
letoch haka'arah o letoch hatamchui. When can you put the spices into
your chicken soup or your טשולנט? cholent? When you have poured it
into your bowl. Now you've got your soup in your bowl, it's
a כלי שני. kli sheni. Go ahead and put spices in. Or
תמחוי. tamchui. What's a תמחוי? tamchui? תמחוי Tamchui is like the tureen.
Okay, so it's not the bowl you eat out of, it's the
serving bowl. But as long as it's in a כלי שני, kli
sheni, go ahead put spices in because a כלי שני kli sheni
does not cook. This is the basic principle. כלי ראשון Kli Rishon
is a problem, כלי שני kli sheni is not a problem. Problem
to put it in the pot, not a problem to put it
when it's in the bowl, even if it's boiling. Okay, now רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, לכל הוא
נותן חוץ מדבר שיש בו חומץ וציר. lekhol hu noten chutz mi-davar
she-yesh bo chometz ve-tzi'ir. You can put spices into anything unless something
that has חומץ, chometz, vinegar
or ציר tzi'ir like a type of a fish brine. That somehow
will make things cook quicker, but without that you can go ahead
and put it into anything. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara what
that means. But before we get to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda I
want to make two points. First of all,
the first point in the משנה, Mishnah do not put spices in
this pot of your chicken soup or טשולנט cholent even if it's
not on the fire, it's boiling hot. What happens if you did
go ahead and put spices in? The assumption almost all ראשונים Rishonim
make based on the earlier גמרא Gemara about כלי ראשון kli rishon
even when it wasn't on the fire and you might remember hard-boiling
the egg by putting it next to the kettle even not directly
on the fire is that if you put these spices in the
soup bowl, in the pot, the טשולנט cholent pot or the soup
pot even not on the fire, it'll be בישול דאורייתא, bishul d'oraita,
it'll be a biblical transgression. However, the משנה Mishnah doesn't say that,
it just says you shall not, it does not say that whether
it's biblical or rabbinic. And I do want to remind you that
there is an interesting position of רמב"ן, Ramban, Nachmanides, who says that
it would only be rabbinic. The only way you would actually biblically
cook is when you put something directly on the fire. If it's
off the fire even boiling hot in a כלי ראשון kli rishon
is only rabbinic. Overwhelmingly the ראשונים Rishonim reject that. They say that
כלי ראשון kli rishon even not on the fire is considered cooking.
If you were to put these spices into the soup bowl, into
the soup pot or the טשולנט cholent pot, you would be and
it was boiling hot, you'd be חייב. chayav. Okay, that's number one.
Now, number two is how hot is the liquid that is the
soup that if I put spices in I'll be cooking the spices
or if I put onions in I'll be cooking the onions? How
hot is it? So here, because of the earlier גמרא, Gemara almost
everybody assumes that it's יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo.
Yes, yes, I'm getting there.
So because the earlier גמרא Gemara says that I cook water when
the water gets יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, they make the
assumption that for the soup to cook something else, for the soup
to cook the onions that I'm going to put in or whatever
or you know the salt or the pepper, as long as the
soup is יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, it'll cook what's put
into it. But you'll notice the משנה Mishnah. doesn't say that it's
boiling, it's רותח. rote'ach. רותח Rote'ach is boiling, that's much hotter than
יד סולדת בו. yad soledet bo. And רש"י Rashi like reiterated that.
רש"י Rashi on the משנה Mishnah says
דמשתשך דכלי ראשון כל זמן שרותח מבשל. mi-shete'shach de-kli rishon kol zeman
she-rote'ach mevashel. A first vessel as long as the liquid in it
is boiling, it will cook other things. Right, so the רש"י Rashi
on the bottom of מ"ב ע"א. mem-beit amud aleph. So
it is possible to argue in terms of you know what is
considered biblical cooking. We normally assume a כלי ראשון kli rishon even
not on the fire once the liquid inside of it is יד
סולדת yad soledet can cook other things. But it's possible to say
no no no biblically it's cooking only if it's directly on the
fire or maybe it's cooking only if the liquid is רותח, rote'ach,
the liquid will cook other things only if it's רותח, rote'ach, only
if it's like boiling. You could have made those qualifications. As a
general rule we assume not. We assume once it's יד סולדת yad
soledet and even not on the fire it will cook other things.
So that's principle number one of the משנה. Mishnah You need a
כלי ראשון kli rishon
and then we add you know even on the fire will be
biblical, even if it's not רותח rote'ach not boiling, even יד סולדת.
yad soledet. But those points could be argued. Now the משנה Mishnah
goes on to say the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who
says that it's a matter it depends whether there's חומץ chometz or
ציר. tzi'ir. So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara,
says to explain רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and then I'll take your
other
question. איבעיא להו Itba'u lehu says
the
גמרא, Gemara the question was raised, רבי יהודה ארישא קאי ולקולא או
דלמא אסיפא קאי ולחומרא. Rabbi Yehuda a-reisha ka'ei u-lekula o dilma a-seifa
ka'ei u-lechumra. When רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says only
if there's oil or vinegar, what's he saying? He's saying even in
a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, even in the Or is he going
on the סיפא? seifa? You, the Rabbis said that you're not concerned
once it's in the bowl, once it's in a כלי שני, kli
sheni, I would be concerned even in a כלי שני kli sheni
if it had vinegar or brine that would make it cook even
in a כלי שני. kli sheni. So is he being strict on
a כלי שני kli sheni or lenient on a כלי ראשון? kli
rishon? So the גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear, דתניא de-tanya רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר omer לכל אלפסין הוא
נותן, le-chol ilfsin hu noten, you can put into any pans, לכל
קדירות הוא נותן, le-chol kederot hu noten, I don't know exactly, an
אלפס ilfas maybe is more like a frying pan, in into any
pans, into any pots הוא נותן hu noten חוץ מדבר שיש בו
חומץ וציר, chutz mi-davar she-yesh bo chomets ve-tsir, except something that has
vinegar or fish brine. So what you see is that רבי יהודה
is even more lenient. Even a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, if it's
not on the fire, will not cook unless it also has in
it vinegar or brine. That somehow will make these things cook more
quickly. תוספות Tosafot says that he's not, you know, some raise the
question like, would he really say nothing could cook without vinegar or
brine if it's not on the fire? Well, maybe he means spices.
Spices would only require this vinegar-brine. But either way, רבי יהודה is
saying that I will not, you תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says only
it cooks in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, not in a כלי
שני. kli sheni. I'm going to say it doesn't even always cook
in a כלי ראשון kli rishon if it's not on the fire,
only in special cases of vinegar or brine.
Question is, okay, what if that's a meat case? Like, you know,
spices are relatively small, they could cook faster.
Alright, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara is going to
get to that right now. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, so now we have the principle putting רבי יהודה aside, that
כלי ראשון kli rishon cooks, כלי שני kli sheni does not cook.
And again, assuming that what you need for כלי ראשון kli rishon
to cook is יד סולדת בו, yad soledet bo, it's not set
explicitly, that's the assumption we make, and we assume that it cooks
דאורייתא even not on the fire, but only כלי ראשון, kli rishon,
not כלי שני. kli sheni. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, תני
רבי חייא, tani Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught, so this
is מלח אינו כתבלין, melach eina ke-tavlin, so I've been saying salt,
maybe because that's the normal spice I put into things, but the
גמרא Gemara now distinguishes salt from other spices. Spice so, and by
the way, one thing that's important to be aware of when we
say the word spices, we naturally think of things like salt, garlic,
vinegar and so on. Not vinegar, salt, garlic, I don't know, pepper,
all
dill, who knows, other types of things. For the גמרא, Gemara תבלין
tavlin very often meant larger things, not like, you know, things like
onions and garlic. Okay? So that raised, and it does raise an
interesting question, I should say about also what's considered to be cooking.
In this, what I mean by that is, there's a whole issue
around tea. Like, you know, can I cook tea, can I use
tea in a כלי שני, kli sheni, a כלי שלישי, kli shlishi,
because look, I see that it gets, you know, that it sort
of, that it makes tea even if it's in a third or
fourth or fifth vessel, so maybe it's cook, you know, maybe it's
considered cooking even not in a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. So, you
know, רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik basically said that that's not cooking, that
you're extracting the tea flavor but you're not cooking the tea leaves.
But cooking is basically when you're using the heat to transform the
object that you're cooking, so that you know the chemical transformation makes
it somehow edible or taste different or whatever. You're not cooking a
tea leaf and now you'll be able to chew the tea leaf
and the tea leaf tastes different. You're just extracting the flavor from
it. So if you think about that, that's also true by spices.
When you put spices in, like, you know, you're basically extracting the
flavor of the spices into the, into the thing or dissolving it.
You're not really cooking the spices.
But if you put in onions or garlic, then maybe you could
say you're actually cooking the onion. You know? So it does raise
interesting questions about what do we mean by cooking. Or you're cooking
the whole stew, you know, and part of the cooking of the
stew is the presence of the spices. So do, you know, what
does it mean to cook the spice? I think that's an interesting
question which is not really fully unpacked. But it is worth noting
that the גמרא Gemara. when it speaks about תבלין tavlin is more
talking about things like onions and garlic. Okay? And now it's going
to contrast that to the question of salt. Yes?
What's the distinction between whether or not you're going to eat the
actual item? You're not going to eat the tea leaf.
Right. You'll eat the salt. Right. Right. That could be. That could
be true. And like also a question like sometimes you put in
a bay leaf, you know, but you don't eat the bay leaf,
you just want the flavor that comes out of it. Right. Right.
So that's a good point. Okay. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara now says about salt as opposed to תבלין. tavlin.
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this: Okay. אמר ליה אביי, amar
leh Abaye, תני רבי חייא מלח אינו כתבלין. tani Rabbi Chiya melach
eina ke-tavlin. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught salt is not like these
other spices. דכלי שני נמי מבשלה. de-kli sheni nami mevashla. Salt will
cook even in a כלי שני, kli sheni, presumably it'll dissolve and
even in a, even in a כלי שני kli sheni it will
also cook. ופליגא דרב נחמן. u-pliga de-Rav Nachman. That argues on רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. דאמר רב נחמן: de-amar Rav Nachman: צריכא מלחא בישולא
כבישרא דתורא. tsricha milcha bishula ke-bisra de-tura.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says: salt needs cooking like the meat of
a cow. The same way if you have meat, you know, some
serious like beef, a side of
It requires a lot of heat in order for it to really
cook. Now the normal salt we buy in the supermarket is basically
already cooked, right, isn't it? Don't they bake salt?
No, no cooking, it's just size of grains. It'll dissolve.
They don't pass it through any heat in the processing of the
salt or anything?
No, it comes right out of the salt mine. It's mined.
Or dry it out.
Really?
Or if it's sea salt it's just dried out.
Okay, okay, that's interesting. Okay, so anyway, so again maybe
the גמרא Gemara, is talking about like a huge chunk of salt,
but again I don't get it because presumably it starts salting the
thing that it's in right away by some of it dissolving. But
again, what does it mean to cook salt? I mean, so this
statement I never really fully got this, but at this statement the
גמרא Gemara is basically saying that salt is, that salt requires a
lot of cooking like, like, you know, like a side of beef
and therefore don't go telling me that salt will cook in a
כלי שני, kli sheni, that's not true. Salt requires a lot of
cooking. So the איכא דאמרי, ikka d'amrei, others say, סבר רב יוסף
למימר מלח הרי הוא כתבלין. sevar Rav Yosef l'meimar melach harei hu
k'tavlin. מלח melach is like other spices, דבכלי ראשון בשלה דבכלי שני
לא בשלה, d'bi kli rishon beshala d'bi kli sheni lo beshala, it
cooks in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, it doesn't cook in a
כלי שני. kli sheni. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
said to him, תני רבי חייא, tani Rabbi Chiyya, רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiyya taught, מלח אינה כתבלין, melach eina k'tavlin, salt is not like
spices, דבכלי ראשון נמי לא בשלה, d'bi kli rishon nami lo beshala,
that it doesn't
even cook in a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. Maybe when it's not
on the fire. In order for salt to cook, it's not enough
that it be in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, it has to
maybe be directly over the fire, maybe it requires a lot of
time. והיינו טעמא דרב נחמן, v'hainu taama d'Rav Nachman, that's why רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says, צריכה מלח בישולא כבשרא דתורא, tricha melach bishula
k'bisra d'tora,
that salt requires as much cooking as like a side of beef.
And therefore, you require even in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, if
you try to put a side of beef into a boiling hot
pot of water off of the fire, you are not going to
cook the side of beef. If you want to cook a side
of beef, you've got to put it directly on the fire, and
the same here is true about salt. One second, so I want
to say this is an extremely important גמרא Gemara from a number
of perspectives. First of all, the issue about the side of beef
and the amount of time. We normally assume that as soon as
you put something on a fire on שבת, that's cooked. Oh my
god, I put it on the fire, I cooked it. But actually,
it's only cooking once it gets it
to a state where it's fit to be eaten. So if you
put a raw piece of meat on the fire and then you
took it off before it got cooked to any serious degree, I'm
not saying what you did was allowed, but you have not actually
cooked because it did not get the thing to
transform it to a position where it's ready and fit to be
eaten. So talking about the side of the beef and the salt
or whatever is important, it makes us realize that things don't cook
instantaneously. The other important point is that this introduces the idea that
there's not one rule for everything. Based on the object it might
require, it might cook to a different degree, כלי ראשון, kli rishon,
כלי שני, kli sheni, and so on. And here's a huge difference
between the first answer of the גמרא Gemara and the second answer
of the גמרא. Gemara The second answer of the גמרא Gemara basically
says, does not admit that anything cooks in a כלי שני. kli
sheni. You need a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. Not only do you
need a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, some things won't even cook in
a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. Something like a side of beef or
salt, even a כלי ראשון kli rishon wouldn't be enough, it would
maybe have to be directly over the fire. But we're not even
allowing that anything will cook in a כלי שני. kli sheni. That's
the second answer of the גמרא. Gemara. The first answer of the
גמרא, Gemara. however, is different. The first answer of the גמרא Gemara
says salt maybe cooks more easily than spices and can even cook
in a כלי שני. kli sheni. Okay, that is hugely significant, not
just because of salt, but because it opens up the floodgates, because
it basically says maybe there are things that will cook in a
כלי שני. kli sheni. Right, this is the one גמרא Gemara that
allows for the possibility that things cook in a כלי שני kli
sheni is maybe salt cooks more easily than spices and will cook
in a כלי שני. kli sheni. And even though the גמרא Gemara
seems to reverse that and give the other approach that salt requires
more, but at one stage the גמרא Gemara allowed for that as
a possibility. So the question becomes do we rule like that and
do we allow for the possibility that some things can cook in
a כלי שני? kli sheni? So תוספות Tosafot says we don't rule
like that. All of the evidence at the end of the גמרא
Gemara is that salt is harder to cook and it needs at
least a כלי ראשון kli rishon if not being directly over the
fire, and nothing cooks in a כלי שני. kli sheni. However, some
say no, maybe we have to be concerned for that position that
salt can cook in a כלי שני. kli sheni. If we start
to be concerned that salt can cook in a כלי שני, kli
sheni, maybe we have to be concerned that other things can cook
in a כלי שני. kli sheni. And then from this develops this
whole category in הלכה halacha called קלי הבישול, kallei habishul, things that
cook more easily. And then we have to be concerned that there
might be things that cook more easily, and all of a sudden
we thought we were so safe once we got something in a
כלי שני, kli sheni, you didn't have to worry at all. Now
we have to be concerned, oh my god, even if it's a
כלי שני, kli sheni, maybe it's a קלי הבישול, kallei habishul, something
that cooks easily, and then even in a כלי שני kli sheni
it's a problem, maybe it's a problem even in a כלי שלישי
kli shlishi or a כלי רביעי, kli revii, who knows, because now
we don't have any strong lines of absolute yes or no. And
this then becomes where a lot of. And this then becomes where
a lot of sort of we are in terms of contemporary הלכות
שבת. hilchos Shabbos. That there are those that say, there are basically
the following opinions, that there are those that say that
basically
you don't have to worry at all about a כלי שני, kli
sheini, although it's rare that somebody would go that far although that
is seems to be the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara But certainly
there's the position that... that the only things you have to worry
about in כלי שני kli sheini are things in which it's like
evidence that they cook very
easily. The general assumption being it doesn't cook in a כלי שני.
kli sheini. Things that it's quite obvious cook very
easily, those are the things that you would have to be concerned
about. That's like the position that the חזון איש Chazon Ish takes.
The position that a lot of us take, sort of followed by,
led to by the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah and the מגן אברהם
Magen Avraham and other אחרונים Achronim is, you basically have to assume
that everything cooks in a כלי שני kli sheini because you don't
know. And the only things that you can assume that don't cook
in a כלי שני kli sheini are... that only the כלי ראשון
kli rishon are the things that are explicitly mentioned in the גמרא.
Gemara And there are two things if you've been paying attention in
the גמרא Gemara that גמרא Gemara says, or three, require a... will
only cook in a כלי ראשון. kli rishon. What are the things
that the גמרא Gemara says will only cook in a כלי ראשון?
kli rishon? What does our משנה Mishnah talk about? A side of
beef. And what's the case in our משנה that it's only a
problem... it's not a problem in the bowl, it's only a problem
in the... תבלין, tavlin, spices. And what the גמרא Gemara said two
days ago, which was water. Water is in a כלי ראשון kli
rishon or water or oil, and the גמרא Gemara just on עמוד
א talked about water in the cup versus water in the bath.
So basically if you take that approach, those are the only three
things we can be confident in that don't cook in a כלי
שני. kli sheini. So if I want to put an ice cube
in my boiling hot chicken soup, that I can do because that's
water. Water doesn't cook in a כלי שני. kli sheini. But if
I want to put some pepper in it, that I can do.
But if I want to put some bread in it, right? Well,
that's a question of בישול אחר אפייה, bishul achar afiyah, which we
haven't gotten through yet. But then I have to be concerned that
maybe things that are not spices and not water and not a
side of beef, those will cook in a כלי שני. kli sheini.
So again there's the... what this גמרא is usually important... one way
of reading it is כלי שני kli sheini you never have to
worry about. Because the גמרא suggested that maybe salt was a problem
in כלי שני, kli sheini, the next step is the חזון איש's
Chazon Ish approach is I think it's a more reasonable one which
is, as a general rule you don't have to worry about כלי
שני kli sheini unless there's evidence that certain things cook very easily,
then you have to worry about כלי שני. kli sheini. The third
approach, which is the most extreme is, you have to worry that
everything might cook in a כלי שני. kli sheini. Everything might be
like the salt possibility of גמרא except the three things the גמרא
says are different. Now
there's one or two final points about this which is, what about
something... first of all there's a discussion about... then it becomes like
very much of a game like what do you call תבלין. tavlin.
Now we said תבלין tavlin are okay, what am I going to
say fits into the תבלין tavlin category? Now the תבלין tavlin category
etc. So let's talk for a minute about the issue about tea.
So the big question about tea like should you put tea in
a כלי שלישי? kli shlishi? Should you do tea essence or whatever,
what do you say about tea? So here
some people say oh tea's not a problem, tea is תבלין, tavlin,
it's
spices. So now it becomes this whole thing about can you fit
something into the תבלין tavlin category? But others say forget that, tea
it's very clear you can make tea in a כלי שני, kli
sheini, כלי שלישי kli shlishi or whatever, you get out the tea
essence so that is something that cooks more easily. So to this
as I said before Rav Soloveitchik responds and he says that's not
cooking just because you get out the essence. And the way other
people try to prove that is they say look I'll show it
to you, if you put tea bags in cold water you'll get
out the tea flavor. So it's not about cooking at all. So
therefore you know that tea is not even though you'll make tea
in something that's not a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, כלי שני kli
sheini or כלי שלישי, kli shlishi,
it's not because it's considered to be like you're cooking the actual
tea leaves, the evidence being that you can do it in cold
water. So anyway this leads to all of the fun discussion. And
the other issue besides the קלי הבישול kalei habishul where tea is
a great example, do you put it in this קלי הבישול kalei
habishul category? Is the question about does the heat of the water
matter? So like Rav Moshe Feinstein was asked maybe even if in
general we allow tea let's say in a כלי שלישי, kli shlishi,
maybe if the water is scalding, there's like boiling like our משנה
רותח, rotei'ach, not just יד סולדת בו, yad soledes bo, maybe that
should also factor in and maybe you should be more strict if
the water is boiling as opposed to if the water is just
hot. And Rav Moshe rejects that. But then it becomes all of
this like field day. The גמרא seems to be working towards very
formal issues, this amount of heat, יד סולדת בו, yad soledes bo,
כלי ראשון, kli rishon, not כלי שני. kli sheini. But with this
little גמרא about salt might be different says that there's no absolute
rules and then it becomes this big field day of what are
things that cook easily? Does it matter כלי שני, kli sheini, כלי
שלישי, kli shlishi, כלי רביעי? kli revii? What counts as תבלין? tavlin?
Does the degree of heat matter if it's יד סולדת בו yad
soledes bo versus scalding? And then it becomes this like big open-ended
discussion. So so much of what we define as cooking is based
on this little גמרא we did about salt.
Yes, I just want to take a step back, I feel like
I'm
getting... You, Michael? Never.
Yeah, how do we know
בישול *bishul* is אסור *assur* to begin with for me? If I'm
thinking about let's say what they did in the משכן *Mishkan*, right?
Were they cooking meat for the משכן *Mishkan*?
Doesn't matter. That's the principle of אב ותולדה *av and toldah*. Once
you get the basic מלאכה *melachah*, then you abstract it. So anything
that is light, you know anything that's cooking, the basic use of
heat on a food to make change its state and change its
edibility or whatever. Okay, but we haven't got there. We're going to
get to it in the seventh פרק *perek*, the whole concept of
אב ותולדה *av and toldah*. Okay, yeah.
Stentsel says an interesting note that water with a small quantity of
salt requires a significantly higher temperature to reach boiling. I don't think
it's actually, I don't think that's true at all.
When I make my pasta, I add, whenever I'm boiling water, I
put salt into it so that it boils quicker.
No, it actually increases the boiling point, but it takes actually a
lot of salt to increase it. But he says that since salt
boils only at a very high temperature after cooking for a long
time, the cooking he said to be like cooking the meat of
an ox.
That's, I don't know, it's surprising to me. Okay. I don't know
if I agree with that, but okay. Yeah, right.
What I find is interesting is that you're generating all these חומרות
*chumros* based on salt, but salt when you throw it into water,
I mean, it doesn't really cook. It just dissociates into sodium chloride,
the water boils off, and you're going to be left with salt
at the bottom of your pot.
Aha, which is the sort of like the ענין *inyan* of the
גמרא *Gemara*, that salt doesn't cook. It doesn't. Right. Which is the
ענין *inyan* of the גמרא *Gemara*. So that's what I said. All
of these חומרות *chumros* come from the first ענין *inyan* of the
גמרא *Gemara*, which the גמרא *Gemara* seems to reject at the end.
And what you're telling us is that actual science, you know, even,
you know, salt does not cook. Salt does not cook.
It's meat you're changing chemical bonds, you're changing protein bonds.
You're not going back. Right, right.
It's crazy because the גמרא *Gemara* opened the door and allowed for
the possibility that it's not an absolute line of כלי ראשון *kli
rishon*, כלי שני *kli sheni*, that creates this whole enormous like world
of חומרות *chumros*. Okay, let's get now to the next משנה *Mishnah*.
אין נותנין כלי תחת הנר לקבל בו את השמן *Ein nosnin kli
tachat haner lekabel bo et hashemen*. Now we're talking about fire, but
no longer about concerns of cooking or fire, more it gets into
a מוקצה *muktzah* discussion. You cannot put a vessel underneath the lamp
in order to catch the dripping piece, oil. Why? Because that oil
that's designated for burning in the lamp is מוקצה *muktzah*, it's set
aside for burning. And therefore, if the vessel, if the plate catches
the oil, then the plate can't be moved because it has מוקצה
*muktzah* on it, and you're making this plate unusable. This is a
principle that you are, אין מבטלין כלי מהיכנו *ein mivattlin kli mehikhano*.
This plate could be used on שבת *Shabbos*, by putting it under
the lamp and catching the oil and now having מוקצה *muktzah* on
it, you're making it unusable, and you're not allowed to make something
that was usable unusable, a vessel unusable on שבת *Shabbat*. That's one
explanation. On שבת *Shabbat*. The other explanation is, is that there might
be a principle that you cannot move something not מוקצה *muktzah* for
the sake of something מוקצה *muktzah*. Okay? אין כלי ניטל אלא לצורך
דבר הניטל *ein kli nital ela litzorekh davar hanital*. So therefore, you
can't move this plate for the oil, since the oil is מוקצה
*muktzah*. So you don't put it under the lamp to catch the
oil on שבת *Shabbat*. ואם נתנו מבעוד יום מותר *Ve'im nesanu mibe'od
yom mutar*. But if the day before שבת *Shabbos* is fine. ואין
עושין ממנו *Ve'ein osin mimenu*, and you can't benefit from the oil
that's on the plate, לפי שאינו מן המוכן *lefi she'eino min hamukhan*,
because the oil is מוקצה *muktzah*, so that's pretty obvious. Okay. אמר
רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*, it's not set aside before. אמר רב
חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*, אף על פי שאמרו אין נותנין כלי תחת
תרנגולת לקבל ביצתה *af al pi she'amru ein nosnin kli tachat tarnigolet
lekabel beitsatah*, you can't put a vessel under a chicken to catch
its egg, the same way you can't catch the oil, because the
egg is נולד *nolad* and it's מוקצה *muktzah*. אבל כופה עליה כלי
שלא תשבר *Aval kofeh aleha kli shelo tishaver*. If you don't want
to step on the egg and break it, you can't catch the
egg in the vessel, but you can put the vessel on top
of the egg. Because by putting the vessel on top of the
egg, you're not making the vessel מוקצה *muktzah*. Right? If something is
holding מוקצה *muktzah*, it's called a בסיס *basis*, and you can't move
a vessel that's holding מוקצה *muktzah*. But if the vessel's on top
of the egg, then the vessel isn't holding the egg, and the
vessel isn't מוקצה *muktzah*. So therefore, you can put the vessel on
top of the egg, but not underneath to catch the egg. Okay?
אמר רבא *Amar
Rava*, מאי טעמא דרב חסדא *mai ta'ama deRav Chisda*? What's the reason
of רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*? קסבר *Kasavar*, תרנגולת עשויה להפיל ביצתה באשפה
*tarnigolet asuya lehapil beitsatah be'ashpah*, a chicken will normally drop its egg,
a hen will drop its egg in a
garbage
dump, meaning so it'll drop it randomly in the street, and people
might step on it. ואינה עשויה להפיל ביצתה במקום מדרון *Ve'eina asuya
lehapil beitsatah bimkom midron*. It's not going to drop its egg at
an incline. The reason you would want to put the vessel underneath
to catch it is to stop it from rolling down an incline.
That's a rare circumstance. What's more common is it'll do it in
the middle of somewhere and you need to put the vessel on
top of it. So here he's saying the difference is not that
in one case the vessel becomes מוקצה *muktzah* because the egg, it's
holding the egg, and the other case it's not מוקצה *muktzah*. The
difference is is that you can do it to protect in a
normal circumstance, but not for a rare circumstance. So it's normal to
have to protect the egg from being stepped
on. And therefore you can put the vessel on top of it.
It's less common that the egg needs to be caught to prevent.
והצלה מצויה התירו, הצלה שאינה מצויה לא התירו.
They
allowed you to move the vessel to save something for a common
scenario that the egg shouldn't be stepped on and broken, but not
for a rare scenario that the egg might roll away and break.
That's rarer, and therefore to put the vessel underneath to catch it
was not allowed. On top of it to protect it, which is
more common, is allowed. And we will continue with this tomorrow. Okay.
Okay, so this seems to be working pretty well here.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yay. Minimum disruption.
Minimum disruption.
Just a pain to set it up.
Well, you set it up. Keep it set up, but still moving
it from the corner. Do you want to put the גמרות Gemaras
over here? I'll put them just to the side.
Oh, you got the laptop and we'll raise money to buy.
Okay, sounds like a deal.